So if I’m in a competitive game and I have
some information about reality, the reality
of the playing field that I’m in then that
information can be a source of strategic competitive
advantage against whoever I’m competing
against and so I have an incentive to withhold
that information from other players and maybe
even disinform the other players.
So we see this is actual games.
This is bluffing in poker.
This is fake left and go right in soccer,
football.
But we also would see this in keeping the
knowledge to ourselves of where the water
is or where the goal is from another tribe
or another kingdom or whatever and maybe even
trying to throw them off the scent trail with
an intentional leaked fake treasure map that
has them going the wrong direction so they
don’t accidentally discover what we discovered.
Things like that.
So within a rival risk context where information
is strategic competitive advantage there is
an incentive to disinform.
And as we get increasing information technology
which is media technology and computational
technology and statistics and all these things
we have, we really have exponential information
processing but applied to disinformation,
the incentive to disinform we have exponential
disinformation capacity which means the ability
to customize inflammatory, fake news, propaganda,
narrative warfare to specific demographics
and all the way down to specific types of
people that are the types that are most likely
for that person to believe, be upset by, affect
their actions.
So we see with social media platforms like
Facebook the capacity to be able to target
the things that are going to be the stickiest
for an individual and the stickiest often
is by appealing to limbic hijacks of what
is scariest to them or hits addiction buttons
the most or creates a sense of ingroup-outgroup
dynamic or things like that.
So when you think about having a society that
has an incentive to both withhold information
and to disinform and you think about a huge
number of different agents who all have increasing
disinformation capacities and you also think
about the radical asymmetry between an individual
just trying to make sense of the world and
a huge platform like Facebook or Google or
a company that is doing split test, optimized
marketing you have an asymmetric information
warfare of the largest powers in the world
with agendas that are not the same as the
agenda of the individual for themselves being
put forth on radically powerful information
technology platforms.
So you look at the world today and whether
it’s climate change or whether it’s what
the extent of the damage at Fukushima is or
what the actual tactical capabilities of North
Korea are or how long we actually have with
coral die off or most any of the things that
are the most critical issues in the world.
What goal other countries or what effect other
countries had in influencing U.S. elections.
No one really knows the most important things
clearly to be able to inform good choice-making
even about how we survive as a species.
So this is critical when we’re trying to
understand the current information ecology.